Leah: Let’s first start by looking
at the origins of open source code.
The idea of making source code open
and freely available, originated in
1983 with an ideological movement.
Richard Stallman a programmer from
MIT, was the informal founder, who
believed that software should be
accessible to programmers to modify as
they wished to hopefully improve it.
He released free code under his own
license under the GNU public license.
Jack: This ideology and new
approach eventually led to the Open
Source Initiative [OSI] in 1998.
The OSI acts as an informational and
governing repository of Open source
software providing rules and guidelines
on how to use it, as well as providing
code licensing information and support.
Leah: Open source code is usually
stored in a public repository
and shared with the public.
Anyone can access it and use the code
independently or contribute to the
design or functionality of the project.
Programmers who have access to it can
change a program by adding to it or
fixing parts that aren't working properly.
Jack: Open source software [OSS] usually
comes with a distribution license
including terms of how developers can use,
study, modify and distribute the software.
When the source code is changed the
OSS must include what was altered as
well as the methods used to alter it.
Leah: Some well known examples of OSS are:
GNU/Linux-operating system
Mozilla Firefox- web browser
GIMP- photo editing suite
Open Office- office suite with word
processing, spreadsheets, and databases
Advantages with OSS are that it is
free and comes with a large community
of users and programmers that
continuously modify the software.
This source code is publicly
available and also opens up
opportunities for new programmers.
The disadvantages are it can have
compatibility issues and by it's nature
it has problems with quality, performance
and security flaws, but the large groups
of programming and coding contributors
identify and fix these issues.
Jack: Let’s now have a
look at Closed source code.
Closed software [proprietary] containing
closed source code is owned by commercial
organisations with creators having
copyright over whatever they create.
But source code can be easy to copy
and take apart to see how it works.
The solution to this is by not
publishing the source code but instead
to compile it into a set of machine
code instructions in an executable
file and sell that to customers.
This is closed source software as it
is difficult for anyone to work out
what the original source code was by
just referring to the executable file.
Leah: Commercial organisations invest
a great deal of money on developing
their software and they want to make
it profitable therefore making it
closed source is a better option.
They will also make it more sophisticated
to attract people to buy it rather than
download open source equivalents which
don't have the same sophistication.
Jack: Some well known examples
of closed source programs are:
Microsoft Windows – the
Windows operating system
Apple macOS – the Apple operating system
Adobe Photoshop – Adobe’s closed
source photo-editing suite
Microsoft office – Microsoft’s
word processing, spreadsheet,
and database software